<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Kings Most Excellent  Majesty. Dread Sovereign, having seen a proclamation wherein your Majesty complains of the injuries you receive in your customs, I could not withhold, but, as in duty bound, humbly present  you with a few of those malignant roots from whence they spring, whereby navigation and trade are also much decayed ...</title>
            <author>Bower, Richard, fl. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08543</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3869A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224295</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64550982</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 64550982</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184380</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08543)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184380)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2862:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Kings Most Excellent  Majesty. Dread Sovereign, having seen a proclamation wherein your Majesty complains of the injuries you receive in your customs, I could not withhold, but, as in duty bound, humbly present  you with a few of those malignant roots from whence they spring, whereby navigation and trade are also much decayed ...</title>
                  <author>Bower, Richard, fl. 1662.</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed by: Richard Bower.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Customs administration --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:184380:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dread Sovereign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving ſeen a Proclamation wherein your Majeſty complains of the Injuries you receive in your Cuſtoms, I could not withhold, but, as in duty bound, humbly preſent you with a few of thoſe malignant roots from whence they ſpring, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Navigation and Trade are alſo much decayed, their luſtre being much concerned in the well management of your Cuſtoms: for thoſe wholeſom Laws provided for the encreaſe of Navigation, and advance of Trade, are intruſted in the ſame hands your Cuſtoms are; ſo that he that ſhall be Ignorant, negligent, or corrupt in the one, cannot be underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, faithful, and diligent in the other: Therefore it being of ſo great concernment not only to your Majeſties Receipt, but to the publique good, I humbly crave your Conſideration in the premiſes following, wherein it will appear that the moſt readieſt ways that can be invented for the ruine of your Cuſtoms is now practiſed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, All Officers are left at liberty, without Bonds, Security, or Oath, given for the faithful Diſcharge of that Truſt impoſed on them, which doth greatly encourage them to act their will and pleaſures towards your Revenues ruine, for their own benefit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As if this were not ſufficient to lead them to betray that Truſt impoſed on them, they are inforc'd by meer neceſſity to fraudulent practices, their Salleries being reduced ſo low, they cannot live upon it; ſo that it is become a Proverb between the Merchant and Officer, <hi>Live, and let live:</hi> Which is, the Merchant and Officer to ſhare your Majeſties Revenue, ſo far as they make it not publique to every eye.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To inforce them to make the quicker and greater ſpoil of your Majeſties Receipt, their Places are made ſo uncertain in the enjoyment of them, that let them be never ſo able and faithful, a ſlanderous Accuſation, laid by ſuch as are either great, or in favor, outs them without audience, which inforces them to provide for the future, and, as the Proverb is, <hi>To make Hay while the Sun ſhines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, The number of ſupernumerary Officers being great, and neceſſitated, will be ſupplied by your Revenues ruine, which makes the ſpoil the greater.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Their beſtowing Places by favor, without regard had to the perſons, parts, and abilities fitting the place or no; by their care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs herein great prejudice to your Receipt doth enſue: For by the ignorance of one Officer there may be as much loſs, as by the kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of another; your Cuſtoms varying as the quality of Goods doth, and one commodity having various denominations, the one ſort ſhall pay three or four times the duty of the other, and through the ignorance of an Officer, the beſt ſhall paſs under the worſt deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The cutting Maſters of Ships off in their Portage draweth an inconveniency upon your Tideſman: for formerly, upon the allowance all Maſters had for Portage, the Tideſman, who hath the whole charge of your Receipt aboard, and cannot ſtir without prejudice to it, could aboard have commanded things neceſſary and convenient, as his Diet, or the like; but now is inforc'd to comply with the Maſter, to do him ſome favor for what he receives.</p>
            <p>The onely Perſons that are by theſe practices diſcouraged, and neceſſitated, are thoſe in whom the ſole Truſt of the Income of your Revenue lieth; who are the two main props and pillars that keep up your Revenue, if faithful; if corrupt, lets it fall to the ground; which perſons are onely two, your Land-Waiter, and Tideſman: For from the firſt Entrance of any Ship or Veſſel into any Port, until delivered, your whole Revenue, night and day, lieth under the Tideſmans charge; and what he doth faithfully preſerve and keep, is to be delivered by your Land-Waiter, according to the true quantity and quality for which the Cuſtom is payd: If the Coaſt, which is moſt ſhamefully ſleighted, were ſecured to conveigh your Receipt into the Ports, and your Tideſman and Land-Waiter but faithful and diligent, your Cuſtoms would have a vaſt improvement: but if neceſſity and opportunity will make a Thief, it is impoſſible your Officers can be honeſt, by what they are now, through diſcouragements and neceſſity, put upon.</p>
            <p>NOw that your Majeſty may have able, faithful, diligent Officers, which are the ſupport of your Revenue; and that they may be ſo preſerved and kept, theſe following Propoſals I tender.</p>
            <p>Let a Pardon firſt be paſt for all Offences hitherto committed; and the reaſon is, I be<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieve very few Officers, either in <hi>London,</hi> or the Out-Ports, but have, as I may ſay, ſold themſelves to the Merchants: And if any Action hitherto they have done, the knowledge whereof will make them uncapable of their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, without a Pardon they muſt be ſlaves for the future, not daring to be any other, for fear their former frauds and bribes be diſcovered; therefore firſt ſet them free, and I doubt not but theſe following preſerves them honeſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let no Officer be emp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyed in the Cuſtoms, but what are bound in good Sums, with good Sureties, for the faithful Diſcharge of their Duty; and he that ſhall betray the truſt on him impoſed, to the prejudice of your Majeſties Receipt, to forfeit his Bond, and loſe his Place, never to be employed more; for the taking them in again, after once convicted, dot<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but imbolden others to commit the like crimes.</p>
            <p>Second<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, Let your Officers be allowed a ſufficient Sallery, if it be ſomething extraordinary, more than a competency, your Majeſty cannot better im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove what you give, except the Merchant were ſo honeſt he would freely pay his Cuſtoms: But otherwiſe, if that it be advanced by your Officers faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and care, or ſpoiled by his negligence and corruption; to enco<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rage them to the one, and prevent them in the other, is to allow them a ſufficient Sallery.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let them have an aſſurance of the certain continuance of their Places, ſo long as faithful; for the parting with underſtanding men, and taking in the ignorant, doth but ſtrengthen your Adverſaries, and weaken your Receipt: for none knows how better to deceive your Majeſty, and help the Merchant, than thoſe that have ſerved you.</p>
            <p>Fourth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, Let the number of Officers be leſſened, who being neceſſitated, and not able to live, muſt make the greater ſpoil: therefore let them be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to as many as are needful; and the extraordinary charge your Majeſty is put to with ſupernumeraries will very much ſupply the extraordinary charge of thoſe Officers neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, That your Majeſty may for the future have able Officers, let none be taken into your Cuſtoms (I mean, below-ſtairs) above a Tideſman; and in caſe a Surveyors place be made voyd by death, or otherwiſe, let the eldeſt Land-Waiter enjoy it; if a Land-Waiters place, the eldeſt Tideſman: this fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hopes of bettering their condition will be a ſtrong tye to keep them faithful; beſides, by this means your Officers will be fitted with parts and abilities, not onely for the place they enjoy, but alſo to judge and inſtruct thoſe beneath them; and it will the more deter them beneath from fraudulent practices, having them above them that have paſt through their places, and underſtand their ways and opportunities.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Let Maſters of Ships have their former allowance for Portage, and the Mariners ſomething, as your Majeſty ſhall think fit, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the Receipt of their Cargo; then ſhall your Tideſman have no engagement lie upon him for thoſe things neceſſary he receives, and the rugged Sailer will be more reſpective, and timerous in acting for the Merchant to your prejudice, for fear of loſing what is his own.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered; Firſt, A competent Livelihood; Secondly, An aſſurance of the certain continuance thereof; Thirdly, The future hopes of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condition will undoubtedly make that man faithful, that hath either any ſpark of honeſty, or common reaſon in him: But if there ſhould be any ſo fooliſh, as not to value theſe, which I think there is none but will; yet the forfeiture of his Bond, and the certain loſs of his employment for ever, will undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deter him from the breach of that Truſt impoſed on him.</p>
            <p>Let but theſe Remedies be forthwith applied, and you will finde in this Vintage what a vaſt improvement of your Cuſtoms will be made hereby, and what a vaſt ſpoil hath been made in your Revenue; to make which appear, this I propound, That there are many Ships gone for <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> and other places, for Wines this year, which came loaden home the laſt year; at their return let a ſtrict care be taken at the delivery of them, and by comparing laſt years Entries with this, it will be found, how ſhamefully ſhort they made out their Tunnage, beſides the great quantities of Wine entred for Vinegar; Vinegar paying but 5. <hi>s. per</hi> Tun, and Wine 6. l. <hi>per</hi> Tun: To make this appear, if your Majeſty think fit, I ſhall uſe my weak endeavors, and give ſatisfaction here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: If then it ſhall appear, that a vaſt loſs hath been in Goods of ſuch bulk and danger in removing, what muſt there be in fine Goods, and others, that are to be conveyed away with more eaſe and ſafety.</p>
            <p>I know not whether I am the firſt in this Work, or no, but I judge I may, the number being ſo few that underſtand it; and of thoſe that do, few but are benefited by the ſpoil of it, beſides the diſcouragements they ſhall meet with that undertake it, their adverſaries being ſo many and great; ſo that, if not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by your Grace, it will ſoon be ſmothered, and the Author, or any other, for the future diſcouraged. There are ſeveral other things practiſed, which are very deſtructive to your Receipt, which at preſent, for fear I ſhould be too prolix, I omit. Therefore I ſhall add no further at preſent: But if theſe few lines, clad in a Ruſſet ſtile, may finde acceptance with your Majeſty, he ſhall further enlarge himſelf, that is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties moſt humble, faithful, and obedient Servant, <hi>RICHARD BOWER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
